

CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

### **OVERVIEW AND OBJECTIVE**

My name is Francois van der Walt. I am a 34 year old from South Africa. Currently looking to immigrate to Canada (Details of immigration progress in the immigration section).

I have a Bachelors degree and Honors in Business (Logistics management more specifically) and previous experience in logistics operations management. More recently I have been involved providing solution within the environment of Business Management Systems.

Through my career I have found that I take fulfillment from providing solutions. During my time in management, I enjoyed that there were always a problem that required a solution. What is also nice about management you tend to have visibility over the finances and other information which gives feedback in terms of whether your solutions are having the desired effect. I have also enjoyed over the last years that my work was mainly providing a software solution to business problems.

My goal at this point is to try and tie my experience and skills of my career and realign this with my original education in business management and logistics.

My ideal position would involve analyzing business processes and being involved with implementing new processes and solutions. However I have a variety of skills which lend me out to many possible positions.



.COM





CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

### **EXPERIENCE**

#### FULL STACK DEVELOPER • SCUBED • AUG 2022 - PRESENT

SCUBED is a south African HR consulting company established in 2000 who developed their own software and eventually expanded that software to include payroll and not just HR functionality. I was hired on a permanent basis in August as a full stack developer. My duties include among others.

- -Analyzing customer and internal stakeholder needs.
- -Planning and designing solutions in line with the above needs.
- -Development of solution in line within these needs within the framework of the existing system.
- -Assisting with building API's as part of larger effort of modernization of the system
- -Report writing using SQL Server Reporting Service
- -Automating and streamlining administrative and other activities through development of applets.

# SENIOR PROGRAMMER HR AND PAYROLL • FSCA – FINANCIAL SERVICES CONDUCT AUTHORIY <a href="https://www.fsca.co.za/pages/default.aspx">https://www.fsca.co.za/pages/default.aspx</a> • JAN 2022 – AUG 2022

Was appointed by the FSCA (Financial Sector Conduct Authority) as a Senior Programmer for HR and Payroll on a 12-month Contract. During my time at my previous company XFour solutions I was allocated to a project for the FSCA. During this project I played a very central and pivotal role in making the implementation of the Sage ERP system a reality. Months after the implementation of the project they had reached out to me.

During my time there my duties were similar to those at XFour solutions outlined in the below section. Some of the biggest achievements from my time there were.







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

- Resolving of the leave issues that the system had and by doing so ensuring helping
  ensure that the FSCA maintain their clean audit track record (They have gone many
  years with a clean audit and the leave was posing a risk to that)
- Being able to assist with establishing business processes that saw business return to using this process after originally abandoning it due to lack of confidence.

#### BUSINESS ANALYST AND DEVELOPER • XFOUR • SEPT 2017 - 31 DEC 2021

XFour is a company that implements and maintains business solutions for clients. These solutions are mainly focused on Human Resources, Payroll and ERP systems. During my time there I would essentially meet with clients to establish their needs and then offer up solutions / alterations within or around the framework of the relevant software solution, which often was Sage X3. I would then be involved in the implementation or development of the solution. My role compared to other developers at the company differed mainly in that I would be involved with more regularity in client interactions and needs analysis. Furthermore, I was more frequently involved with providing business solutions when activities outside of programming was required.

My biggest achievement during my time at XFour was being able assist a client called the FSCA (Financial Services Conduct Authority) where I fulfilled a pivotal role in getting the project over the line.

## FINANCIAL ADVISOR • OPTIMUM FINANCIAL SERVICES AND LATER DISCOVERY • OCT 2013 - SEPT 2017

Spent 4 years as a Financial advisor marketing financial products including Medical aid, Life insurance, investments and Short term insurance. During this time I learned a lot about pension funds, investments etc. The biggest thing I learned however is that I do not enjoy sales jobs.







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

## MANAGEMENT TRAININEE AND CONTRACT MANAGER • IMPERIAL LOGISTICS • JAN2011 - SEPT 2013

This Section will be numbered to illustrate to cater for all the positions fulfilled during my overarching time with the parent company Imperial Logistics

#### 1. Management Trainee January 2011 – February 2012

#### Tasks & Responsibilities

The Management Trainee Program was originally intentioned as a structured program which provided training and exposure to different areas of the business. The program was a Human Resources initiative that stretches 2 years. As part of this program, you are assigned to a supervisor/overseer. In my case an area manager named Johan van Aswegen. I mention intentioned in the intro as the program was all the above and was fantastic. At times you would oscillate between the mentioned training curriculum and getting helping out in line with operational requirements. At the end of the day you are receiving this training within the larger context of a functioning business so this makes complete sense. When these operational requirements came calling it would be introduced as "A good opportunity" which it was. It had however become a bit of a joke among trainees regarding managers liberal use of the word "Good opportunity". As part of this program I went department to department to get an idea of the functioning of the business. Spent time weeks finance among others. Of all these exposures my favorite was spending 2 weeks in workwear learning about Truck Maintenance and workshop operations (I got to be a mechanic's assistant for a period of time which was a fun experience). My biggest success was almost directly upon arrival at Imperial there was a transport sector strike. I was asked along with two other trainees to head up an impromptu strike information center. I later learned that a large part of my successes later had come due to how had handled this task. It was a task very visual to the whole business and a good opportunity to make a name for yourself.

2. Broco Logistics Management Solutions - Site Controller March 2012-May 2012







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

I was transferred to Broco (A different company within Imperial Logistics). The company I was allocated to as a trainee got a contract with Pick and Pay. However, it differed from the normal operations in that we were merely monitoring and consulting and did not own the infrastructure/trucks. The only staff we really had on the contract was a team of 12 operational guys to monitor operations of other contractors and report back (This included me).

#### 3. Imperial Dedicated Contracts. - Contract Manager

May 2012 - October 2013

The manager I worked for previously had phoned me up with a "good opportunity". This time it truly was a good opportunity. To understand the rest of my time at Imperial Logistics Group some background is needed. Imperial Dedicated contract provided transportation services in a very decentralized model. They would have clients whom they provided long term transport contract to. The vehicles would be branded in the customers branding. The vehicles would be parked and permanently allocated to that client. The staff of the contract would also be allocated permanently to that client. There would be an on-site manager and supervisor/s. These operations varied in size from 2-40 vehicles. This offered a young ambitious person as myself a good opportunity to manage the full scope of a business while receiving administrative support and oversight within a larger company.

The first contract I managed was a company called Incledon <a href="http://www.incledoncape.co.za/">http://www.incledoncape.co.za/</a> (12 Vehicles -20 staff members). I managed this for about a year and will always have fond memories of this time I then moved on to my second contract **Nampak Corrugated** (12 vehicles - 2 sites 60 staff).

After about 6 months at Nampak I started managing another site down the road from my own Mondi Plastics. During this time, I was still involved in handing over the Nampak site to my successor. It was still in this handover phase that I made a call that I no longer wanted to be involved in operations. The stresses and rigors of managing such large transport operations at a relatively young age had started taking a toll on me. I took some leave and was released by the company on the basis of retrenchment.







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

### **PERSONAL TRAITS**

- People skills. I have an ability to gain peoples trust and respect through honesty fairness and respectfulness. When managing my first contract at Imperial I ran a tight ship. I enforced some things on principal which I retrospectively sometimes feel I might have been harsh. When there was a violent union strike action employees would come to work and then hope that they could sit in the yard and still get paid (The company takes this loss as the client won't cover that expense for your employees not to drive and get paid). Most if not all other managers allowed this. I simply explained to them that as much as I fear for their safety that it is the union which they are members of that are striking and not the company. So if they come to work they must be willing to drive or stay at home and not get paid. Being harsh I was deemed fair. Upon leaving They made a plea to the manager replacing me to please continue to treat them with the levels of respect and fairness with which they were being treated during there time working for me.
- Determination. The project which we worked on for the FSCA was a trying on at the best of times. During the last stretch where I played a central role. There was a feeling of gloom around the meetings, and many were not expecting the project to be completed in time. As we started achieving successes, I would often be praised for my hand in that. I would then respond with the fact that the staff of FSCA really are getting sold short by some of this praise as some of those staff members were carrying me at times. I later after the project when already working for FSCA asked why had the guys gotten behind me and supported me. The response I got was along the following lines. "Many people had understandably given up hope in the project when I came along. I arrived and was not willing to give up. No matter what setback were uncovered each morning in the meetings I continued to come up with plans and solutions".







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

- Capable of commutating efficiently on any level within an organization. I am fairly well read and travelled and have work in a unusually diverse settings (From working Closely with head of departments at a Regulatory body to loading trucks and working as a mechanics assistant for a week). I believe this helps Having done the IELTS tests for immigration purposes which seems to confirm that I have sufficient language skills to communicate efficiently.
- Creative in coming up with solutions. When I was at university my Logistics Honours class was made up 65 students. Among this crowd I was a middle of the road student and did not boast any sports cultural achievements nor was I member of any student bodies etc. There was a Two week exchange type concept sponsored by USAID. It was part of a larger project between the University of Michigan and the University of Johannesburg. There would be 2 students selected from this honors group two visit the university of Michigan for 2 weeks. I really wanted to go but didn't think I had much of a chance to be selected from such an Elite group. One night sitting in the Library (I was supposed to be studying) inspiration struck. I realized that most of the people writing the motivational essay and going for the interview would spend all there time talking about how great they were as students or Leaders of student bodies etc. I decided I would say nothing about what qualifies me to go. I would simply write an essay which states how great this opportunity is and about why Michigan would be a very insightful place to visit from a logistics perspective. I ended up getting chosen until this day I am very proud of this and believe were it not for my out of the box thinking I would not have been selected.
- Sense Responsibility and pride in my work. I believe my success in my career is driven by this more than anything else. It can be a double edge sword as taking on to much responsibility can be stressful. At the same time success has followed me in the periods where I took on responsibility which at times were perhaps not even my own.







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

### **SKILLS**

- -C#
- -HTML
- -CSS
- -JavaScript
- -React
- -Node.js
- -SQL Server Management Studio
- -Visual Studio 2022 and 2019
- -Visual Studio Code
- -.net Framework
- -.net Core
- -Asp.net Webforms
- -SQL
- -SQL Server Reporting Service
- -SAP Chrystal reporting
- -Sage X3 People (Functional and development skills) 5 years' experience
- -Sage X3 BMS Distribution Module Completed course as well as certification exam

.COM





CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

### **EDUCATION**

#### BCOM HONOURS LOGISTICS MANAGEMENT • 2010 • UNIVERSITY OF JOHANNESBURG

Major Subjects: Supply Chain Management and

Strategic Logistics Management

Other Subjects Maritime Economics and Quantitative Techniques

#### BCOM LOGISTICS MANAGEMENT • 2007 - 2009 • UNIVERSITY OF JOHANNESBURG

Major Subjects: Logistics Management and Marketing Management Other Subjects: Transport Economics, Accounting and Microsoft Office

#### MATRIC EXEMPTION • 2002 – 2006 • FLORIDA HOËRSKOOL

Subjects Afrikaans, English, Math, Accounting, Commercial Law and Economics

#### REFERENCES

- Zinhle Dlamuka> FSCA > HRSIS > +27 66 248 3357
- Bellina Sebesho > FSCA > Head of Department Financial Management > +27 73 660 0961
- Andrew Brooks> XFour Project Manager > +27 83 455 6280
- Jaco Smit > XFour > Director > +27 84 585 5509
- Shaun O Reilly > XFour > Director > +27 82 56 54 284
- Johan van Aswegen > Imperial Logistics Operations Executive > 083 449 6590







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

• Dr Peter Kilbourn > University of Johannesburg - Senior Lecturer > See attached reference letter

#### PERSONAL INFORMATION

• Full names: Hendrik François van der Walt

• Age 34

• Marital Status: Married

• Children: 1

License and Vehicle: Yes
Address: Irene Pretoria
ID Number: 8802045035087

• Availability: Immigration in Progress

#### **IMMIGRATION PROSCESS**

ME and my wife have submitted our application for permanent residency through the express entry portal. We have completed most if not all of the tedious administrative requirement surrounding this (Police clearances, IELTS exams and WES certification of qualifications). We posses the necessary means to immigrate, funds, qualifications to find work, we are well researched and have visited Canada to help ensure that this is something we want to do.







CURRENT INDUSTRY: BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS

As it stands at this point in time the company consulted estimates that we should be invited to apply from the pool by June 2021. However finding a job on a work permit would help expediate this matter.

The have provided some reference numbers below which they state we should use in our efforts to look for work.

a. your Express Entry profile number: E003104119

b. your Job Seeker validation code: 4737

### Comprehensive ranking system (CRS)

The CRS is the points-based system we use to assess and score your profile and rank you in the Express Entry pool.

Your overall score 452



